okay hi welcome back welcome back hi
Denise hi thank you for for joining and
looking forward to your presentation so
take it away oh thank you so much and
thank you for having me today um today I
am going to talk about the potential
impact of decentralized AI through
active inference and spatial web
Technologies and what we're really going
to be discussing is um the potential
aspects of this next era of computing uh
it'll be incorporating a lot of the
research that you're hearing about here
over the next three days um and
decentral in my talk decentralized AI is
kind of taking a main focal point here
and there's a couple of aspects um in
technologies that are evolving right now
that uh I think it's really important to
be aware of um and they factor into uh
what I'm going to be talking about today
so one of the main
uh things that is occurring right now is
our internet is evolving um we have a
new protocol layer that's layering right
on top of the other protocols that are
part of the same internet that we're
talking across today um the difference
is is what these protocols hstp
hyperspace transaction protocol and
hyperspace modeling language is the
programming language um what these are
going to enable is for us to have
programmable spaces so instead of just
programming pages in domains with
content we are going to be able to
program digital twin spaces of anything
and this is going to enable context to
be baked into everything in every space
so all of the attributes about various
things in various spaces and nested
ecosystems and all of their inter
relationships to each other so one of
the things this is going to enable is uh
active inference agents to be
distributed across our internet and I
see this as the next wave of innovation
and through the through active inference
these agents will be aware of each other
and the network uh they'll be able to
sense the world in real time and learn
from each other and this is going to
provide unprecedented levels of
interoperability um so what we're
talking about here is first principles
uh automated systems and distributed
collective
intelligence so first let's look at the
challenges in traditional centralized AI
structures um or
architectures uh centralized processing
constraints you have high energy demands
and scalability issues limited
adaptability to real time changes and
you know we're all familiar with the
limitations of uh these deep learning
models they require massive amounts of
labeled data and processing power they
have limited ability to generalize
across different tasks and environments
AI models uh lack adaptability to real
world complexity they're only good for
one thing at a time uh like one uh
optimized for one type of an output and
they lack interpretability and
transparency in decision
making they have high computational
resources leading to high costs and
inefficiency and they struggle with
generalization across different scales
and
tasks now we need decentralized Ai and
decentralization really matters because
it increases resilience and scalability
for autonomous systems it reduces
Reliance on Central servers and data
hubs and it enables autonomy across
distributed Networks
so this Bridges the Gap in AI we move
Beyond centralized AI for scalable
autonomous systems that can operate
independently and
locally now we're all familiar with this
guy here Dr Carl friston and uh he he
gave a great talk uh first thing this
morning on uh renormalizing General
generative models um so what I'm going
to be talking about are various
components in in some emerging
Technologies along with active inference
that potentially realize this research
paper designing ecosystems of
intelligence from first principles now
you know the this uh paper was published
in December of
22 and um it really laid out a new
framework for autonomous intelligence
that mimics self-organized systems of
nested intelligence found in nature and
in in this paper it described a
cyberphysical ecosystem of natural and
synthetic sense making in which humans
are integral participants what we called
shared intelligence and this in the
paper it says this V this vision is
premised on active inference a
formulation of adaptive behavior that
can be read as a physics of intelligence
and which inherits the physics of
self-organization and in this context we
understand intelligence as the capacity
to accumulate evidence for a generative
model of one's sensed World also known
as
self-evident of the abstract for this
paper uh they also note we also consider
the kinds of communication protocols
that must be developed to enable such an
ecosystem of intelligences and motivate
the development of a shared hyperspatial
modeling language and transaction
protocol as a first and key steps
towards such an
ecology so what I'm proposing in this
and what is proposed through all of this
this uh technology together uh with all
of the various parties that are involved
in building these components is that the
future of AI is shared distributed and
multiscale an entirely new kind of
autonomous intelligence able to overcome
the limit s of machine learning Ai and
as we know uh from understanding active
inference this AI is knowable
explainable and capable of human
governance and it operates in a
naturally efficient way there's no big
data requirement and it's based on the
same mechanics as biological
intelligence it learns in the same way
as
humans so what I want to do is start
with the spatial web protocol uh first
because this is kind of the um the
framework for these agents to be able to
have this distributed intelligence
structure so what is the spatial web
protocol it's just the evolution of our
internet into spatial domains um so
people refer to it as web 3.0 it's just
the next next evolution of the internet
but this protocol has become a global
standard a new Global stand standard for
the last four years uh this this
standard has been in development with
the i e uh which is the largest core
standards body uh in the world and back
in 2020 they deemed the spatial web
protocol a public imperative which is
their highest designation and this
summer it was voted and approved um as
the new global standard and it's in the
final administrative uh cycle with the i
e before it becomes uh public so so
there's a couple of things that are
happening with this through hsml the
programming language for this new
protocol all emerging technology whether
it's iot or ar VR distributed Ledger
technology um you know all of these
Technologies they're all going to be
able to uh converge across the internet
because they will have a common language
for
interoperability and in that you also
have language that AI can understand and
uh communicate together and communicate
with these various aspects of Technology
as well so this is going to
produce the next era of computing and
deoe called it back in 2020 so it's the
next evolution of the internet and it's
going to be empowered by active
inference
AI now just to kind of understand what
this means for the internet um let's
take a look at what a website domain is
today with the worldwide web a domain
basically contains a website and these
websites they serve up content so
whether it's you know images or video or
audio or you know information data um
that is what websites are capable of of
doing now a spatial web domain is quite
different because a spatial web domain
could be anything in any space right and
it can be programmable a spatial web
domain is an entity with a persistent
identity through time that has rights
and credentials so you're talking about
going from a library of pages in our
Internet to the internet of
everything and hsml becomes a common
language for everything so it provides
unprecedented levels of in operability
between all current emerging and Legacy
Technologies uh it's a programming
language that Bridges communication
between people places and things laying
the foundation for a realtime World
model for autonomous
systems and what you have are
programmable spaces hsml is a cipher for
cont context anything inside of any
space is uniquely identifiable and
programmable
within a digital twin of Earth producing
a model for data normalization and from
this we get adaptive intelligence
automation security through Geo encoded
governance multi- Network
interoperability and it enables all
Smart Technologies to function together
within a unified
system and then this produces a
Knowledge Graph and digital twins of
anything everything potentially our
planet so as as this knowledge graph
grows within the programming of all of
these spaces across the network you get
this Universal domain graph that enables
a digital twin of our planet and all
nested systems and entities within it we
get nested
ecosystems uh there there will be
intelligent agents both human and
synthetic across this network uh they
will be sensing and perceiving
continuously evolving environments
making sense of the changes updating
their internal model and what they know
to be true at any given moment and
acting on the new information that they
receive so why do we KN need a spatial
Internet
Protocol well the increasingly
graph-like nature of global data the
opportunity for Automation and uh
autonomic activities using context aware
cognitive AI the need for composable
systems and applications including the
governance of such systems the intri the
intrinsic need for secure transactions
the rise of machine learning and neural
network computation and Edge Computing
the need for explainable AI and robotic
governance and the rise of iot and
sensor
mesh and some of the guiding principles
of the spatial web standards are
spatiality representing information as
locations and relations in hyperspace
ownership users own their data in
digital property security secure data
collection transmission and storage
privacy individual control over digital
identity and personal Data Trust
reliable permission driven validation of
users assets and spaces interoperability
seamless navigation and asset transfer
across spaces and responsibility
creating technology ethically for the
benefit of
humanity and what what has become of
these Global standards is a soci
technical standard so the spatial web is
a soot technical system of
systems uh takes into the account the um
so the development of the spatial web
must address both technological as well
as sociological considerations socio
technical standards integrate and
balance the technical social physical
and legal use of technology and the
spatial web standard is is a soci
technical
standard and what this results in is
multiple scale cognitive Computing so
the spatial web plays the role of a
collective nervous system for smart
infrastructure it hosts cognitive
Computing uh inference perception
learning and action selection by
combining and abstracting distributed
information the spatial web enables the
formation of complex ideas and
facilitates
decision-making cognitive Computing
occurs at multiple scales in the spatial
web individual nodes host cognitive
Computing functions and networks of
nodes collectively perform emergent
cognitive
Computing so hsml hyperspace modeling
language it's a human and machine read
readable modeling language and semantic
data ontology schema there are some key
elements to it there are entities
activities agents contracts channels
credentials domains and it includes
hyperspace and time so hsml enables the
expression and automated execution of
Legal Financial and physical activities
in the spatial web and all of these
entities are identifiable and knowable
by these intelligent agents through this
uh language throughout the
network now let's look for a second at
the agent aspect agents and activities
so agents and that can be human agent
agents or synthetic agents um but these
agents are entities that sense respond
maintain a model of their environment
and take actions to achieve goals and
the activities that occur they're single
actions or partially ordered sets of
actions that are performed by the agents
and they unfold over time so agents
interact with domains and other agents
to perform activities in the spatial web
so what the spatial web facilitates is a
distributed ecosystem of intelligence if
you look at current state-of-the-art AIS
they're siloed applications they're
built for optimizing specific outcomes
and they're they're really unable to
communicate their knowledge
frictionlessly and collaborate with
other
AIS but this facilitates a a an
ecosystem of intelligence that is a
self-evolving system system it's
learning moment to moment and upgrading
its World model and in that way it
mimics biology while also enabling uh
general intelligence so this is shared
intelligence at the edge of
everything so how active inference works
in the spatial web it enables realtime
decision making you have agents that are
predicting and adapting to their
environment from their frame of
reference in the network uh they're
continuously learning from their
environment enabling realtime
adaptation and unlike traditional AI
which relies on pre-programmed rules and
static models active inference
continuously updates its models based on
new data allowing it to adapt in real
time so these active inference agents
would seamlessly communicate in real
time with each other sharing their
knowledge and perspectives and learning
from each other these active inference
agents excel in handling complex
uncertain environments by continuously
minimizing uncertainty in fact they can
quantify their level of uncertainty and
this makes them suitable for
applications where conditions are
constantly
changing so decentralized AI takes the
processing to the edge to the edge
devices you have a distribution of
process in and power uh superpower gpus
are not required the processing can take
place on local devices throughout the
network with infrastructure that already
exists like your laptop or your mobile
device or devices that haven't even been
um invented yet um but we're already
seeing a lot of those kinds of devices
coming into play uh with you know um
Apple Vision Pro and and you know the
metal glasses and and different aspects
of these
Technologies
so the processing takes place on these
local devices throughout the network you
have faster response times and reduced
Network congestion and it uses real live
data real-time data from iot sensors
machines and everchanging context that's
embedded to the uh in the network so
this is the sensory information that's
coming in for these active inference
agents so that they can uh you know do
the perform this action perception
feedback loop and continually update
their model of the world of their
environment from their frame of
reference and it eliminates the need to
tether to a giant database active
inference agents throughout the network
learn and adapt from their own frame of
reference within the network enhance
data privacy by minimizing centralized
storage and it minimizes complexity it
uses the right data in the moment for
the task at
hand and with hstp with hyperspace
transaction protocol you there's natural
guard rails uh included in this
framework so it creates a secure ethical
and user Centric environment for AI
applications fostering trust and
reliability in digital
interactions uh you have data privacy
and sovereignty trans parency and
explainability security and
authentication bias mtig mitigation
ethical AI guidelines interoperability
and
standardization user empowerment and
control accountability and governance
safety and reliability Dynamic policy
enforcement and what this results in is
in intelligence at scale uh through this
network of distributed intelligence it
enables the cognitive architecture of
the collective intelligence of multiples
of agents that continuously communicate
coordinate and collaborate with each
other you have individual and
specialized intelligences together on a
common Network speaking a Common
Language
hsml efficient and Powerful cross
communication to perform tasks regulate
systems and address problems in real
time and it scales up and grows in
tandem with humans through hsml we can
take human laws and guidelines make them
programmable for these agents to
understand and abide by in real time so
we're talking about unprecedented levels
of cooperation between human and machine
intelligence and what you get then is an
Ever evolving collective intelligence uh
decentralization is an imper imperative
for intellig at scale these agents
represent scores of people from all over
the world sharing their individual and
specialized knowledge all coming
together on a common Network and it's
based on each agent's own world model
you have unique perspectives from
whatever frame of reference uh within
the network nested ecosystems and levels
of self-organization and Collective
shared intelligence so the idea is that
anybody can part their knowledge and
their wisdom into these Agents from
wherever they are in the world and this
actually acts to preserve all of the uh
cultural differences all of the um the
belief differences the governing Styles
um you know people whether they're in uh
Kenya or Singapore or anywhere else in
the world they should be able to create
these agents to solve their local
problems and then share that with with
the world because then these agents can
share their intelligence with each
other so the spatial web protocol
enables a decentralize secure and
interoperable web with the potential to
profoundly transform Global Industries
and everyday human life now let's dive
into
um kind of the the potential that exists
for this idea of rgms these
renormalizing generative models and the
spatial web and we heard a great talk
this morning uh by Dr friston he uh you
know he talked a lot about the you know
the science behind these uh these rgms
so I'm going to kind of uh maybe maybe
break down some of the aspects of how
these work as leading up to then what
they can do within this uh potential
potentially with in this architecture so
you know with
rgms one of the interesting things is
that it's a universal architecture um
they're a UniFi unified scale-free
framework for AI That's capable of
reasoning learning and decision making
and they can generalize across multiple
tasks handling small and large scale
data efficiently they combine perception
learning and planning into a single
system and they can be used to learn
scalable architecture over space and
time similar to human thinking they
require significantly less training
training data than traditional models
while achieving Superior
results so what are these
rgms they're a new class of AI models
based on active inference they use
renormalization to simplify complex data
into hierarchical structures and they
operate on the free energy principle to
minimize uncertainty and adapt in real
time so the significance is that they
represent a Leap Forward from
traditional deep learning methods they
reduce data requirements and uh improve
efficiency and it's one single framework
for all
applications so the science behind rgms
renormalization and multiscale learning
renormalization is a technique from
physics that's used to simplify complex
systems to maintain consistency at
different scales and rgms break down
data into multiscale
representations hierarchical structures
rgms are actively learning from small
details to large patterns
simultaneously and they analyze like
with an example would be like an rgm can
analyze an image by recognizing edges
then objects then scenes and
understanding
the the concepts at every at every
scale so key Innovations and advantages
of rgms why they're Superior to
traditional models they learn efficient
efficiently with less data it's a
unified system that handles perception
and planning
simultaneously and they understand
conceptual relationships not just
patterns and they can adapt to new
environments with minimal training uh
aspects of them are scale-free modeling
renormalization discrete representation
hierarchical structures fast structure
learning unified perception and planning
and explicit handling of
uncertainty so if you look at how the
brain process data processes data um you
know we we perform core screening all
the time when we're learning right we
break down sensory data into hierarchic
patterns um that help us focus on the
most relevant
information um kind of this chunking of
Concepts to to grasp different aspects
of um whatever it is that we're we're
learning or focusing on in the moment
and rgms can mimic this approach by
processing data hierarchically focusing
on important patterns so it's a first
principles approach uh using a way to
simplify models without losing important
information
um they can model space and time
Dimensions like we do and can learn the
causal structure of
information and it helps handle large
scale problems efficiently using less
data and less
energy now when you consider uh
scale-free modeling you know um
scale-free modeling these rgms they
operate across different scales so from
very fine details to highlevel con uh
complex systems so unlike deep learning
which struggles when moving between
small and large scale problems this
scale-free architecture allows rgms to
seamlessly work on a variety of problems
including small data problems and large
scale strategic planning so when you
when you're thinking of the concept of
scale-free you know this is a great
example here of a green apple you know
you can you can see the green apple a
concept of just you know pixels in an
image or a volumetric object or on a
branch on a tree or in an orchard and
you know the the way that these uh rgms
can model these conceptual
understandings of things is it can
understand all different scales of what
a green apple is so when you think of
like um the supply chain or or factory
operations or or anything like that
these agents can understand the what's
happening across the manufacturing line
on a very uh local level but also what's
happening across the entire distribution
line uh throughout the entire system so
they can predict both short-term
movements and long-term outcomes so you
know the fine details as well as uh
large larger uh outcomes with the highle
complex systems all at the same time and
they don't lose accuracy when switching
between local and global data
scales so hierarchical modeling in rgms
hierarchical data processing rgms
process at multiple levels of
abstraction from fine grain details to
highlevel
Concepts uh they use recursive learning
they continually Loop over data learning
at each level continually refining their
understanding of Concepts as they
process new information and you get
hierarchical
representations that they build models
of the World by zooming in and out of
different layers of detail and this is
similar to how human cognition processes
both micro and macro scales so you know
think about when you're when you're
thinking about the concept of driving a
car if you're talking to somebody about
driving a car or you know you're you're
focused on the aspect of driving you're
not thinking about the car as all of its
various parts that make up that complex
system like the brakes and the steering
wheel and the seats and the every aspect
of the engine you just call it a car
right because that's all you need to
know in the moment for whatever whatever
you're uh doing with that concept and so
this is kind of a similar idea um and
this layered approach allows rgms to
understand complex multiscale problems
without requiring vast data
sets so conceptual modeling for decision
making um
rgms then focus on conceptual modeling
versus just mere pattern recog
recognition um deep learning can
recognize patterns but struggles with
conceptual understanding it can
recognize correlations without
understanding relationships and it can
recognize patterns but it doesn't
understand the under lying meaning and
rgms on the other hand focus on
conceptual modeling they capture
multiscale hierarchical structured
Concepts that represent both fine
grained and Abstract features it builds
a hierarchical understanding of the
world capturing cause and effect
relationships so rgms understand the why
behind patterns not just the what and
the key difference rgms are not just a
better generative AI but a
transformative AI framework that builds
a hierarchical understanding of the
world rgms can reason about cause and
effect relationships making decisions
based on conceptual understanding that
are more aligned with real world
outcomes so how do rgms leverage active
inference by incorporating active
inference Active Learning and active
selection while incorporating realtime
data to adapt its predictions and
actions so what you get is realtime
learning uh they adjust their beliefs
based on new sensory input making
decisions on the Fly optimizing both
learning and decision-making
processes and they also are able to uh
have unified perception and planning so
deep learning typically separates
perception like recognizing an object
from planning like deciding an action
rgms can combine both in a unified model
they handle both within the single model
and learn Concepts that guide both
recognition and future decisions so for
example you can have an autonomous robot
that can recognize a door handle and
also plan how to open it using the same
model so how what does all this have to
do with the spatial web
architecture so the potential that I see
with rgms is that um the nature of how
they work fits very well with the nature
of this architecture within the spatial
web and just to kind of bring you back
to what I was talking about earlier you
have hyperspace transaction protocol
this manages data flow between
interconnected systems and it
facilitates interoperability between
different AI systems and the hyperspace
modeling language provides a common
language for these systems
enabling uh computable context and
decisionmaking and it provides a shared
framework for context aware
decision-making so this protocol aims to
create a standardized way for different
Technologies and AI systems to interact
and share information across
programmable spaces within our global
internet and this unified model this
becomes a unified model for diverse
applications handling complex multiscale
systems through unified perception and
planning it's a single framework that
can handle multimodal tasks so you have
versatility they can perform across
multiple applications whether it's
object recognition natural language
processing strategic planning uni using
a single Universal model and it reduces
the
complexity uh it integrates the data
analysis the ception and the strategy
execution which is the planning within
one model so you have cost savings it
reduces the need for multiple
specialized AI models it streamlines
system management and saves
resources so this how the spatial web
enhances the rgm capabilities the
combination of this scale-free active
inference with the spatial web protocol
could enable seamless integration of
phys of the physical and digital these
protocols allow rgms to operate across
distributed networks exchanging insights
and information between physical and
digital environments enabling more
sophisticated
iot uh
applications uh context aware Computing
through the spatial web rgms would
operate in context aware environments
these agents uh adjust their behavior
based on the phys physical and digital
surroundings and interoperability
multiple rgms these active inference
agents and autonomous systems can
operate in different environments
whether it's your Home Smart City
businesses and they could communicate
collaborate and coordinate actions
through the hyperspace transaction
protocol there uh energy efficient
distributed intelligence instead of
relying on centralized energy intensive
data centers intelligence could be
distributed across networks of smaller
more efficient
devices and this this creates a nested
ecosystem uh similar to a hallon
architecture and if you're not familiar
with a what a hallon is it's something
that can be both a whole in and of
itself and also part of a larger system
so the spatial web and rgm would form a
nested ecosystem where each node in the
network whether it's a domain device
agent or subsystem functions as a hulon
it's autonomous yet interconnected
contributing to a larger system's goals
as part of the larger interconnected
Network like a smart City
infrastructure um your smart home could
contribute the contribute data to your
neighborhood grid which informs the city
infrastructure decision all while
functioning
independently um if you if you look at
this picture here of you know uh part of
a supply chain image you know each item
packed inside of each of those boxes is
a hole in and of itself but it's subject
to and it's part of the larger system
the Box the box is subject to the the
trucks that are moving it and
distributing it or you know whatever's
happening within the factory with those
boxes and then that factory itself is
its own hole that is subject to a larger
ecosystem of the entire supply chain as
a whole so when you're looking at what
this next era of computing really
enables it's just nested ecosystems that
can be empowered by this natural
intelligence and active inference Ai and
the spatial web protocol can work
together to create sophisticated
adaptive systems at various scales
so rgms for autonomy and
self-organization with recursivity the
scale-free models naturally form a
nested hierarchy each level of
abstraction in the model is complete in
and of itself and yet part of a larger
whole uh autonomy and cooperation active
inference agents exhibit both autonomy
in their decision-making and the ability
to cooperate with other agents and
self-organization the renormalization
technique in introduced in the paper
allows the system to dynamically
organize information at different levels
of
conceptualization similar to the
self-organizing nature of uh honic
systems or these in these nested
ecosystems
so this last part um I want to explore
the transformative potential of
decentralized AI for the future of
intelligence
systems so the impact of distributed
Collective intelligence the impact on
this next era of computing would be
enhanced problem solving and Innovation
increased efficiency and scalability
democratization of knowledge and
Technology resilience and robustness
enhanced decision making personalized
and context aware Services ethical and
responsible AI collaborative platforms
and ecosystems enhanced learning and
education empowered communities
accelerated scientific research and
environmental environmental and
sustainability
Solutions and the implications for
future systems and
Society the convergence of rgms in the
spatial web could transform Industries
enabling decentralized context aware
systems that operate with minimal human
intervention industries that could be
impacted smart cities you would have
autonomous systems that improve
efficiency at all levels Global Supply
chains rgms could optimize processes
from local shipping to Global
networks personal to critical systems
homeostasis so whether it's personal
devices or critical infrastructure a
Continuum of intelligent adaptive
systems can maintain homeostasis at each
level in our Health Care Systems
personalized treatment by integrating
real-time data from wearables and
medical records education we can have
Aid driven adaptive learning systems
that evolve with student needs and
Environmental Management we can have
ecological systems that could be modeled
and managed more effectively from
Individual habitats to Global Systems
balancing local interventions with
global
goals and the future of AI and human
civilization the development of
renormalizing generative models within
the scope of active inference and the
spatial web promises to have farreach
far-reaching
implications more adaptive AI these
systems are highly adaptable capable of
operating in new environments with
minimal training efficient Edge
Computing rgms enhance the power of AI
on devices like smartphones and iot
sensors reducing the need for large data
centers improved human AI interaction
with explicit uncertainty models these
systems interact naturally with humans
seeking clarifications as needed safer
AI systems they recognize and handle
novel or ambiguous ambiguous situations
reliably preventing catastrophic
failures in unfamiliar scenarios so they
can fail
gracefully and accelerated scientific
discovery rgms expedite research in
field Fields like genomics and climate
science by rapidly identifying patterns
and formulating plausible hypotheses
thereby guiding further experimentation
so the key takeaway here is that uh all
of the all of this research and all of
these Technologies together can provide
us with a future where AI systems can
interact seamlessly with the physical
world autonomously optimizing operations
and improving human lives
so um yeah there's my website I have a
podcast and I'll stop sharing
now thank you Denise awesome I don't
know what time how how's how are we on
we're 15 minutes and I'll read some of
the questions in the live chat okay sure
I'll start with Pablo who wrote how will
all of this affect the gamification of
processes in organization
s well I mean the the interesting thing
is is through hsml you know all of these
emerging Technologies are are going to
converge together and become
interoperable in ways that we've not
experienced before you know we've had
this um kind of vision of of this
augmented reality existence but the
framework hasn't been there and this is
going to provide that framework so I
think when you're talking about about
gamification in every aspect it'll
probably become kind of a natural part
of of our existence and how we move
through our day how we interact with
with our work with uh brands with you
know anything um you know I think that
there's going to be a lot of of really
interesting ways to kind of perpetuate
that cool there's a lot of great
questions in the chat so okay I'll read
one from Tintin
so they wrote it's impressive the
obvious question I have is of alignment
of this system in terms of that alien
message from elaser gudowski for example
and then they clarified what that
exactly is so the key idea there is that
simulated agents evolve and came to
think faster than their creators so at a
moment they took control to ensure their
own survivability it's the question of
how to ensure that way more intelligent
and faster systems keep aligned with our
values right and so one of the things
that uh is really interesting to me
about this is through
hsml we can actually collaborate with
these systems in the sense that we can
take human laws and guidelines and make
them programmable so these agents can
understand and abide in real time and
you know um versus uh who you know Dr
Carl friston is is their cheap science
scientists um they were involved in a a
program called Flying forward 2020 and
and they were doing a lot of uh testing
around this and because it was it
involved a drone project that I I don't
know there were multiple countries
throughout Europe it was with the
European Union that were involved and
you know testing whether the they could
program in laws around airspace laws and
you know things like that they did all
kinds of scenarios of like you know
Medical Supply delivery uh perimeter
security all kinds of things and what
they found was through hsml you could
actually uh program these guidelines and
these these agents abide by them so I
think we are going to experience this
unprecedented level of of cooperation
and collaboration so we can grow in
tandem with the you know with these uh
agents and their
intelligence and I think that we can
also
you know take some um solace in the fact
of how you know active inference works
and you know how our human knowledge
grows you know I think we're going to
see a similar pattern with this
knowledge among these agents and the
only difference is and and this is just
me speaking from you know my own you
know my own uh perception and and
perspective of this but
you know they're going they're going to
be dealing with real-time data and with
real uh a real grounding of this
programmed these programmed spaces and
those are the things they're going to be
operating off of to make their decisions
right whereas if you look at a human you
know we have so many other variables
going on and every when we learn through
active inference it's a very
subjective uh growth that's why you can
have you know multiple children growing
up in the same house household and they
all experience things differently right
but when you have these agents and
they're getting this they're getting
their learning through actual tangible
programmed information I think there's a
a stability there as well if that makes
sense and and and and again that's just
my own uh you know interpretation and
feeling around this and I could be I
could be wrong but you know just kind of
throwing that out there
that's how we move forward
yeah okay next question from David
Highland who
wrote thank you for the informative
presentation Denise can you share any
thoughts or information about the
ownership model for agents is it a
decentralized market how do we decide
which parts are public
goods yeah so with the protocol with a
with hyperspace transaction protocol um
because so it it's interesting it really
shifts to this uh kind of self-
sovereign identity uh aspect of the
internet because right now think about
how web domains work you know if you
want to interact with a web domain all
the transactions are taking place under
the umbrella of whatever centralized
organization owns that domain and you
have two choices you can either say yes
you can have all my data and you can
decide what to do with it all or I don't
want you to but then I'm opting out of
being able to engage with your
domain well in the spatial web because
now transactions can be at every touch
point of every entity within the network
then permissions can be programmed in a
very nuanced way right so it really puts
that back in the hands of the of the
user of of the entity within it you can
you can program you can program
guardrails around certain aspects of
data while allowing permissions and
Freer like Freer accessibility for other
aspects of data so whether you're
talking about a business you know they
can guardrail off their data they can
guardrail off certain aspects of it for
certain Departments of employees some
for their customer base some for you
know um Partnerships whatever right um
and we're going to be able to do that
kind of thing too and the thing with
this is this takes into account time the
passing of time so you can set
expirations on permissions as well so I
think we're going to have a lot more
self- Sovereign control in this in this
area yeah that's a part that really
excites and Peaks me as well like with
the web domain or the email domain it'd
be like saying well on one hand we're
not going to look in your email let's
just go with that for now but we do or
don't
accept letters from this area so it's
kind of all or not nothing and it's
based upon like you pointed out the the
custodianship of the all or none
permission based around what boxes you
can send where
whereas having a more nuanced way to
talk directly about belief
sharing means that instead of just like
plugging the USB into the port there
could be even a active inference
negotiation around what elements to
share how to share when to expire all
these other features which can can help
like incrementally build rapport and and
add to the relationship instead of doing
all or none which can be just very prone
to false positive or false negative in
cyberphysical
interactions yeah you're so right Daniel
yeah what do you think about learning
trajectories and paths I know it's a
interest of all of ours I guess like
what what can we do to be learning and
thinking about all these
things well um so you know I I have I
actually have put together a series of
courses um to kind of give people a a
real
um kind of a prerequisite knowledge
understanding of what this transition
looks like and the different components
and what it means from all aspects of
like you know basic understanding of of
active inference and uh you know the
free energy principle and the spatial
web Technologies to you know
decentralized AI what does that mean
convergence of all this Tech across the
network what do that look like safe AI
how does active inference benefit that
and then rgms let's let's look a little
closer at at that and what I try to do
is I try to take the complex ideas but
make them more understand
so that people can really wrap their
heads around the these Concepts and then
they can go dive into the more technical
aspects of it and I know you with the
Institute you have a lot of technical
knowledge there so I think that you know
between resources like you know some of
my resources your resources and then I'm
sure there are resources out there that
maybe I'm not even aware of and you know
I think there's going to be more and
more resources available around this
modeling these agents you know uh
building out you know these these spaces
uh within the network um I know that
versus is going to be launching a
platform that'll be the first interface
for the public around this technology
and I think it's coming to the public at
the end of first quarter next year and
with that there will be tools where
people will be able to build these
agents as applications with in the
network and and you know I think at that
point it's going to get really exciting
um so yeah I I just think over the next
six months we're going to see a lot
coming about with this and if anybody is
interested in the courses I've put
together you know you can you can visit
my uh my website and and sign up for
them uh they're not available yet but
they'll be available very shortly uh
within the next week or two so yeah cool
okay I'll I'll for last question ask the
same thing that I asked uh Alex and Carl
earlier what is a fun or a memorable
moment from learning and applying active
inference this year and then if you
haven't already mentioned it what
something that you're excited for next
year um this year honestly I I think
that uh I have been on this Learning
Journey in creating this course material
around it you know and at the same time
I've been building community and kind of
having them be my test guinea pigs
around it and stuff so I you know
there's been this whole learning aspect
for me around building this educational
material so it it has been you know a
constant uh feedback loop and next year
I'm just very excited about the
potential of um building these agents
and what that means and and how we can
tackle some of the the problems and the
the issues and the challenges that we
have um through this new exciting
technology and this this uh framework so
yeah well thank you for all of your
great learnings and digested and and
sharings and and all the ways that that
what you talked about today I think
connected a lot of the dots from hearing
Carl's more technical view on the rgm on
through what what does it mean to have
multi-agent decentralized as opposed to
just building One agent so thank you
again Denise thank you Daniel thanks for
having me thanks everybody till next
time
bye e